Marshall Ryder World War II aeronautical chart collection
Geography and Map Division, Library of Congress
Marshall Ryder World War II aeronautical chart collection 1940-1944
G5701.P6 coll .R9 Ryder
Marshall, Ryder
26 items
1 folder
Geography and Map Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
The collection consists of 26 aeronautical charts that date to World War II. Among them are 16 charts that depict locations in Europe and 8 that depict locations in the United States. The materials were compiled by Marshall Ryder, who served in the U.S. Troop Carrier Command during World War II. He was aboard a C-47 that dropped paratroopers from the 82nd Airborne Division on D-Day, June 6, 1944. Ryder annotated some of the charts.
Provenance
The collection was donated July 14, 1998 to the Geography and Map Division.
Access and Restrictions
The Marshall Ryder World War II aeronautical chart collection collection is open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Geography and Map Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Marshall Ryder was born April 14, 1918 in St. Paul, Minnesota, and died November 25, 2014. Ryder served in the Troop Carrier Command for the United States during World War II. He was aboard a C-47 that dropped paratroopers from the 82nd Airborne Division on D-Day, June 6, 1944.
Scope and Content Note
The collection consists of 26 aeoronautical charts of Europe and the United States. Some charts are annotated.
Arrangement
The Marshall Ryder World War II aeronautical chart collection collection is organized in two series.
Series I: Charts of the United States
Series II: Charts of Europe
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Ryder, Marshall, 1918-2014, compiler.; Ryder, Marshall, 1918-2014.
Organizations
Great Britain. War Office. General Staff. Geographical Section; National Ocean Survey; United States. Army Air Forces. Troop Carrier Command, 9th.; United States. Army Map Service
Subjects
Aeronautical charts--Europe.; Aeronautical charts--United States.; World War, 1939-1945--Europe--Maps.; World War, 1939-1945--United States--Maps.
Form/Genre
Aeronautical charts.
Container List
- Series I: Charts of the United States
  8 items
  - Los Angeles (R-2) April 9, 1942, 1
    1:500,000
  - Dubuque (V-6) June 4, 1942, 2
  - Twin Cities (W-6) November 26, 1942, 3
  - Virginia (N.W. 32 1/2 - 88) November, 1942, 4
    1:1,000,000.
    Black and white.
    Includes two plotted courses.
  - Austin (P-5) January 14, 1943, 5
    1:500,000.
    Includes notations, plotted courses, and calculations.
  - San Diego (Q-2) February 4, 1943, 6
  - NE United States aeronautical chart for radio direction finding (23DF) February 25, 1943, 7
    1:2,000,000.
    Two copies.
  - Kansas City (T-6) March 11, 1943, 8
- Series II: Charts of Europe (Folder 1)
  18 items
  - Stettin (NE 52/14), 1940, 9
    Ordnance Survey.
    Verso: Dumfries, Scotland map, legend in German.
  - Berne (NE 46/6), 1941, 10
    A.M.S. reprint of 1941 Ordnance Survey.
  - Brest (NW 46 1/3 - 5 1/2), 1941, 11
  - Nice (NE 42/6), 1941, 12
    2nd edition Ordnance Survey.
    Includes course plottings.
  - Bremen (NE 52/6), 1942, 13
    Cloth mesh backing.
  - Lyon (NE 44/2), 1942, 14
    1:500, 000.
  - Praha (NE 50/14), 1942, 15
    Verso: A.M.S. 1:100,000 map of Forcalquier, France, 1943.
  - Wien (48/14), 1942, 16
    Verso: Goole und Pontefact, Blatt Nr. 32, in German.
  - Kolberg (NE 54/14), 1942, 17
    Verso: 1:80,000 Falaise, France, legend in German.
  - Toulouse (NW 42/2) September, 1942, 18
  - Berlin (NE 52/10) September, 1943, 19
    A.M.S. reprint of 1940 Ordnance Survey.
  - Brest (M30/10 & L 30/1), 1943, 20
    1:250,000.
  - Dijion (NE 46/2), 1943, 21
    3rd edition Ordnance Survey.
  - Graz (NE 46/14), 1943, 22
    Verso: 1:50,000 Boston, England, legend in German.
  - Leipzig (NE 50/10), 1943, 23
    2nd ed. Ordnance Survey.
  - Marseille (NE 42/2), 1943, 24
  - Torino (NE 44/6), 1943, 25
  - The Border (Scotland - England) Sheet 4, 1944, 26